A Guide to the Lewis F. Powell Jr. Papers, 1929-1998
Washington and Lee University, School of Law, Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives
- Retirement 1987-1998
  - Trip Files
    - Colonial Williamsburg Foundation Board Meeting, November 14-16,1991 (Box 351)
    - Ryan Lecture, Georgetown University Law Center (Box 351)
    - Dedication of Powell Chapel, November 24,1991 (Box 351)
    - Bar Association of the District of Columbia Annual Banquet, December 6,1991 (Box 351)
    - American Bar Association Bill of Rights 2000 Conference, December 17-18,1991 (Box 351)
    - Federal Administrative Law Judges Conference Dinner, March 28, 1992 (Box 352)
      Potomac, Maryland
    - Dedication of Powell Wing, Washington and Lee University School of Law, April 2-4,1992 (Box 352)
    - Virginia State Bar Pro Bono Award to Oliver Hill, April 23,1992 (Box 352)
    - Walter J. Stark Chair, Wilmer Institute, May 1,1992 (Box 352)
      Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland
    - Hollins College Honorary Degree, May 15-17,1992 (Box 352)
    - American Law Institute Meeting, May 13-14,1992 (Box 352)
    - Long Island University, May 10,1992 (Box 352)
      Brookville, New York
    - Fourth Circuit Judicial Conference, June 24-27,1992 (Box 352)
      The Greenbrier, Hot Springs, Virginia
    - Colonial Williamsburg Foundation Board Meeting, November 12-15,1992 (Box 352)
    - Dedication of Arnall Patz Chair, Wilmer Institute, April 29,1993 (Box 352)
    - American Law Institute Annual Meeting, May 11-14,1993 (Box 352)
    - Annenberg Dinner, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, June 5,1993 (Box 352)
    - Eleventh Circuit Judicial Conference, May 16-19,1993 (Box 352)
      Hilton Head, South Carolina
    - Fourth Circuit Judicial Conference, June 23-26,1993 (Box 352)
      The Homestead, Hot Springs, Virginia. Includes speech, Changes In the Practice of Law.
    - Wilmer Ophthalmological Institute, July 6,1993 (Box 352)
    - Elliot Smith Wedding, July 31,1993 (Box 352)
      Virginia Beach, Virginia
    - American College of Trial Lawyers Meeting, September 21, 1993 (Box 352)
      Washington, D.C. Includes speech, A Brief Review of the History of the ACTL and Its Accomplishments.
    - Swearing-In of Frank Wisner as Under Secretary of Defense, October 7,1993 (Box 352)
    - Virginia Historical Society Dinner In Honor of Powell, October 22,1993 (Box 352)
    - Colonial Williamsburg Foundation Board Meeting, November 12-14,1993 (Box 352)
    - Dedication of Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Federal Courthouse, December 9,1993 (Box 352)
    - Alfalfa Club Dinner, January 29,1994 (Box 353)
    - Distinguished Citizen Award, February 28,1994 (Box 353)
    - Virginia State Bar Pro Bono Award, April 26,1994 (Box 353)
    - Bar Association of the District of Columbia Fellows Dinner, May 10,1994 (Box 353)
    - American Law Institute, May 17-20,1994 (Box 353)
    - Fourth Circuit Judicial Conference, June 29-July 2,1994 (Box 353)
    - Investiture of Justice Stephen Breyer, September 30,1994 (Box 353)
    - Metropolitan Club Party, October 4,1994 (Box 353)
    - Lee Integrity Award, October 14,1994 (Box 353)
      Sratford Hall Plantation, Stratford, Virginia.
    - Alfalfa Club Dinner, January 28,1995 (Box 353)
  - Appointment Calendars
    - Desk Calendars, 1987-1998 (Box 353-A)
    - Desk Calendars, 1995 (Box 353-A)
  - Funeral 1998
    - Donations, 1998 (Box 353-B)
    - Sympathy Notes, 1998
      - Friends and Relatives, 1998 (Box 353-B)
      - General Public, 1998 (Box 353-B)
    - Flowers and Gifts, 1998
      - Flower Cards, 1998 (Box 353-B)
      - Record of Gifts, 1998 (Box 353-B)
    - Mourners, 1998
      - People Who Called, 1998 (Box 353-B)
      - Funeral Register, 1998 (Box 353-B)
    - Printed Materials
      - Program and Arrangements, 1998 (Box 353-B)
      - Clippings, 1998 (Box 353-B)
- Materials by Form
  - Photographs (Box 355-358 and oversize)
    Unprocessed.
    - Family, 1907-1996 (Box 355 & oversize 6 & 8)
    - Military Service, 1942-1946 (Box 356 and Oversize 7)
    - Public Events, 1955-1995 (Box 357-357A and Oversize 7)
    - U.S. Supreme Court, 1971-1987
      - General, 1971-1987 (Box 358)
      - Portraits, 1971-1987 (Box 358A-358B and Oversize 8)
        Includes photos of Powell, the Court and law clerks.
    - Portraits of Others (Box 359)
  - Audio-Visual Materials
    - General, c.1955-1971 (Box 354)
    - U.S. Supreme Court, c.1971-1990 (Box 354A-354D)
  - Scrapbooks 1920, 1944-1956 (Box 359-359A)
    Includes boyhood stamp album; bombing of German oil refineries; and two volumes of Democrats for Eisenhower, 1952 & 1956.
  - Clippings c. 1927-1998
    Arranged by topic.
    - Re Lewis F. Powell, Jr.
      - Appointments to Commissions and Boards (Box 359B)
      - Awards (Box 359B)
      - Civil Disobedience (Box 359B)
      - Colonial Williamsburg (Box 359B)
      - Communism (Box 359B)
      - Crime (Box 359B)
      - Crime Commission (Box 359B)
      - Defense (Box 359B)
      - Education (Box 359B)
      - Hunton & Williams (Box 359B)
      - Legal Aid (Box 359B)
      - Supreme Court Nominations (Box 359B)
      - Virginia State Bar Association (Box 359B)
      - Washington and Lee University (Box 359B)
      - World War II and Code Breaking (Box 359B)
      - United State Supreme Court (Box 359C)
      - Retirement (Box 359C)
    - Josephine Rucker Powell (Box 359B)
    - Josephine McRae Powell (Box 359B)
    - Mary Lewis Gwathmey Powell (Box 359B)
    - Lewis F. Powell III (Box 359B)
      - St. Christopher's School (Box 359B)
      - Washington and Lee University (Box 359B)
      - Hunton & Williams (Box 359B)
  - Printed Materials (Box 360-363A and Oversize.)
    This series does not include Justice Powell's chambers and personal library. (See Separated Materials in Administrative Information section.) The entire contents of the library are included in Washington and Lee University's online catalog. Most publications can be retrieved by entering Powell Chambers Library as a title search.
    By forms or materials.
    - Maps (Oversize Mapcase)
      - Plats
        - Bear Island 1929-1960 (Oversize 1)
          Related to section 2.2.2.1 of these papers.
        - Rothesay Road Property 1934-1964 (Oversize 2)
          Related to section 2.2.3.7.2.1 of these papers.
        - Sheltering Arms Hospital, 1962 (Oversize 3)
          Related to section 8.1.3.2 of these papers.
        - Huguenot Land and Brandermill Lot, 1963-1974 (Oversize 1)
          Related to sections 2.2.3.7.4.4 and 2.2.3.7.4.5 of these papers.
      - Military Maps
        - Annotated Map of Europe, Front Line as of May 1, 1944 (Oversize 5)
          Related to section 3.1 of these papers.
        - Vietnam, Blue Ribbon Defense Panel Visit to Hawaii and Southeast Asia, 1970 (Oversize 5)
          Related to section 6.5.4.6 of these papers.
    - Publications
      - American Bar Association
        - American Bar Association Journal and American Bar Association News, 1953-1970 (Box 360)
        - Annual Meetings, 1937-1959 (Box 360)
        - Communism, 1962 (Box 360)
        - Constitution, By-laws, and Procedures, 1937 and 1960 (Box 360)
        - Directories, 1937-1939 and 1958 (Box 360)
        - Judicial Administration, c. 1942 (Box 360)
        - Law Day, c. 1958-1964 (Box 360)
        - Professional Responsibility, c. 1959-1965 (Box 360)
        - Regional Meetings, c. 1958-1964 (Box 360)
        - World Peace Through Law, c. 1958-1963 (Box 360)
      - American Bar Foundation c. 1955-1971 (Box 361)
      - American College of Trial Lawyers, c. 1957-1970 (Box 361)
      - Awards c. 1948-1993 (Box 361)
      - Biographical, c. 1947-1988 (Box 361)
      - Brochures, c. 1938-1966 (Box 361)
      - Civil Disobedience, c. 1966-1969 (Box 361)
      - Colonial Williamsburg, c. 1977 (Box 361)
      - Crime, c. 1965-1967 (Box 361)
      - Defense
        - General, 1957-1988 (Box 361)
        - Blue Ribbon Defense Panel, 1970 (Box 361)
      - Ephemera, c. 1964-1982 (Box 361)
      - Invitations, c. 1969-1989 (Box 361)
      - Re Magna Carta, c. 1963-1966 (Box 362)
        Related to section 7.9 Virginia Magna Carta Commission.
      - Menus, c. 1972-1978 (Box 362)
      - Newspapers, c. 1963-1966 (Oversize OS Folder 12)
        Includes: Ring-tum Phi,November 21, 1928, April 17, 1929 & November 10, 1971; W & L Law News, March 30, 1989; Southern School News, March 1956; Richmond Mercury, March 20, 1974; The Daily Record, May 26, 1941; Richmond News-Leader, November 21, 1956 (part).
      - Political Handbills and Pamphlets, c. 1934-1968 (Box 362)
      - Programs, c. 1970-1993 (Box 362)
      - Reprints, 1987-1993 (Box 362)
        Writing by or about Powell.
      - State Constitutions, c. 1961-1967 (Box 362)
        Related to section 7.10 State Constitutional Commission.
      - Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia, c. 1960-1965 (Box 362)
        Records and briefs.
      - United States Supreme Court
        - General, c. 1964-1998 (Box 362)
        - Blank Stationery, c. 1972-1988 (Box 362)
      - Washington and Lee University Football, c. 1970-1974 (Box 362)
  - Artifacts
    Arranged by forms of materials.
    - General c. 1942-1998 & n.d. (Box 363)
      Contents include (but are not limited to): Gavels, eyeglasses, passports, driver's licenses, medical record cards, smoking pipe, wallet, military insignia, brass door identification plates, and college memorabilia.
    - Medallions, c. 1946-1997 & n.d. (Box 364)
      Contents include: Empty boxes for Legion of Merit and Bronze Star; Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation Medal; National Security Agency Cipher Wheel, 6 November 1987; LPMS Squiggle, 1994-1995; Virginia Cultural Laureate, 1981; Marble from Richmond's Union Station, 1977; Marshall-Wythe/College of William and Mary, June 4, 1972; American College of Trial Lawyers Medal for Excellence In Advocacy; Orison S. Marden Leader in Professional Responsibility and Legal Education; Whitney North Seymour Medal, Columbia Law School; Great Leaders Award, Southwestern Legal Foundation, May 1980; American Law Institute 50 Year Member, c. 1997.
    - Plaques and Busts c. 1972-1993 & n.d. (Box 365-367 and on exhibit)
      One plaque and one bust are on display in the Powell Office and the Powell Archives Office respectively.
    - Certificates and Diplomas c. 1929-1996 (Box 368 and oversize)
      Includes: Earned and honorary academic degree diplomas and citations; and awards of merit and distinction.
    - Textile Artifacts, c. 1942-1996 & n.d. (Box 369-)
      - Washington and Lee University, c.1926-1931 (Box 369)
        Letter sweater, fraternity hat and athletic supporter.
      - Army Uniform and Equipment, c.1942-1946 (Box 369 & 374-376.)
        369: Cap, wool jacket, pants and necktie; 374:leather jacket, wool jacket, pants, and hat; 375: 4 wool shirts, 1 cotton shirt, 2 pair wool trousers, 1 pair cotton trousers; ribbed wool zip-front sweater; 376: shearling lined leather flight helmet, wool cap, cotton cap, gas mask pouch, cloth belt with attached pouch, olive colored wool knit watch cap, 4 pair wool socks, brown leather gloves, tan leather gloves; tan duffel bag; Oversize; sleeping bag, canvas suitcase.
      - Academic Regalia
        - Columbia University Academic Regalia, c. 1978 (Box 371)
          Gown, two caps and hood.
        - Academic Hoods, c.1960-1988 (Box 372)
          Institutions represented include: Hollins College, University of South Carolina, Yeshiva University, Kenyon College, Wake Forest University, Old Dominion University, American University, Tulane University, Brigham Young University, and Virginia Commonwealth University. Several hoods are unidentified.
        - Judicial Robe, c.1972-1994 (Box 373)
          Artifact accession #1999:010A.
    - Army Awards, Memorabilia and Equipment, c.1942-1946 (Box 377 and oversize)
      377: Army issue pocket watch, address book, eagle pin, insignia, dog tags,Legion of Merit, Croix de Guerre with Palm, Bronze Star, Mein Kampf(1940 cloth cover edition), small linen draw string pouch, 2 German banknotes. Oversize: canteen, photo interpreter's kit.
    - Furniture, Fine Art and Miscellaneous (Oversize Map case, on exhibit, and oversize shelves)
      Fine Art: Pen-and-ink portrait of Powell by Egerton; Caricature of Powell ( It's the Only Way by Gib Crocle (sp. ?) IX, 1987; Four Utah landscapes etched in copper plates, presented by University of Utah Law School Alumni Association, 1982; Print of Howard Christy Chandler's Scene of the Signing of the United States Constitution; Print of Patrick Henry Arguing the Parson's Cause by George Cooke (Presented to Powell as Virginia State Bar Pro Bono award for 1991.) Powell's Supreme Court Bench chair is on permanent display in the Law Library Reading Room. A letter box from Powell's undergraduate days in oversize storage.